Sultan Mahmud Sajal

☑ sxs2561@psu.edu

smsajal.github.io

+1-814-380-3595

Research Interests

My research focuses on **workload analysis** and **performance evaluation** of **Cloud Computing Systems**. I am especially interested in faithfully scaling, analysing, synthesizing and, supplementing cloud workloads to facilitate realistic experimentation in both academia and industry. Much of my research has explored how different characteristics of the workload affect the performance of the system under diverse conditions and how to enhance the workload to satisfy specific needs while preserving crucial characteristics.

Education

Expected Spring, 2024

Ph.D. in Computer Science and Engineering

The Pennsylvania State University

Thesis topic: Improving the Fidelity of Trace-Driven Experiments in Cloud

Computing Systems

Advisors: Timothy Zhu and Bhuvan Urgaonkar

2013 - 2017

B.Sc. in Computer Science and Engineering

Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology

Thesis topic: An Empirical Study on the Growth of New Languages and Their

Users in Stack Overflow **Advisor:** *Rifat Shahriyar*

Publications

Sajal, Sultan Mahmud, L. Marshall, B. Li, S. Zhou, A. Pan, K. Mellou, D. Narayanan, T. Zhu, D. Dion, T. Moscibroda, and I. Menache, "Kerveros: Efficient and Scalable Cloud Admission Control," in 17th USENIX Symposium on Operating Systems Design and Implementation, (OSDI '23), 2023.

Sajal, Sultan Mahmud* and Hasan*, Rubaba, T. Zhu, B. Urgaonkar, and S. Sen, "*TraceSplitter: a new paradigm for downscaling traces*," in Proceedings of the Sixteenth European Conference on Computer Systems, (*EuroSys '21*), **Equal Contribution*, 2021.

Professional Experience

May, 2022 - August,2022

Research Intern at Cloud Operations Research (CORE), Microsoft Research.

- Mentors: Luke Marshall, Beibin Li, and Ishai Menache.

May, 2021 - August,2021

Research Intern at Gray Systems Lab (GSL), Microsoft.

- Mentors: Abhishek Roy and Joyce Cahoon.

August, 2018 - Present

■ Graduate Research Assistant and Graduate Teaching Assistant at The Pennsylvania State University.

- Advisors: Timothy Zhu, Bhuvan Urgaonkar.

- Collaborator: Siddhartha Sen (Microsoft Research).

October, 2017 - July, 2018

Junior Software Engineer at Reve Systems.

- Manager: Golam Md Muktadir.

Research Experience

The Pennsylvania State University

Mentors: Timothy Zhu, Bhuvan Urgaonkar, and Siddhartha Sen (Microsoft Research)

- Topic: Facilitating Usage of Background Traffic for Realistic Experimentation in Cloud Systems [2023 Ongoing]
 - Motivate the need for collecting and using background trace with foreground trace
 - Develop methodology to define background trace in different contexts and enable efficient collection of background trace
- Topic: Upscale Workloads from Cloud Infrastructure and Large Datacenters [2020 Ongoing]
 - Developed novel upscaling techniques of real workload to enable faithful systems experimentation under varying loads
 - Explored the reason and scenarios where the existing upscaling approaches fail to show superiority of our approach
- Topic: Downscale Workloads from Cloud Infrastructure and Large Datacenters [2018 2020]
 - Downscale cloud workload while preserving important characteristics to facilitate realistic systems research and industry prototyping
 - Proposed novel techniques for realistically downscaling workloads that preserve important characteristics such as arrival process and performance

Cloud Operations Research Group (CORE), Microsoft Research

Mentors: Luke Marshall, Beibin Li, and Ishai Menache

- Topic: Efficient and Scalable Cloud Admission Control in Azure [May,2022 Dec, 2022]
 - Developed novel techniques for admissions control to guarantee SLA to both allocated and reserved capacity while maximizing resource efficiency
 - Extended existing simulator to plug-in different admission control techniques for comparison

Gray Systems Lab (GSL), Microsoft

Mentors: Abhishek Roy and Joyce Cahoon

- Topic: Development of Flight Simulator for Spark Jobs [May,2021 Aug,2021]
 - Create realistic benchmark for Spark Workloads from query traces
 - Generate synthetic representative datasets for the benchmark

Awards

2023, 2020	Student Grant, USENIX Symposium on Operating Systems Design and Implementation
	(OSDI)

2021 Registration Grant, Sigmetrics 2021

2019, 2018 Student Travel Grant, ACM Symposium on Cloud Computing (SoCC)

Technical Scholarship, Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology

2012 Higher Secondary Certificate Scholarship, Dhaka Education Board, Bangladesh

Junior Scholarship, Dhaka Education Board, Bangladesh

Skills

Programming Languages Java, Python, C++, Scala, C, R, Scheme, Assembly (Intel 8086)

Analysis Tools MATLAB, Weka

Frameworks Apache Spark, Android, Spring-Boot, JPA, JSP, Scikit-Learn, Bootstrap

Technologies AWS Services and SDK, Azure Services and CLI, Docker, Git

References

Timothy Zhu

Assistant Professor

Department of Computer Science and Engineering The Pennsylvania State University



timothyz@cse.psu.edu

Siddhartha Sen

Principal Researcher Microsoft Research in New York City



sidsen@microsoft.com

Bhuvan Urgaonkar

Professor

Department of Computer Science and Engineering The Pennsylvania State University



■ buu1@psu.edu

Luke Marshall

Senior Researcher Cloud Operations Research (CORE) Microsoft Research



luke.marshall@microsoft.com